Guide to the Montana Archaeological Association records 1980-1996
Montana Historical Society
Montana Archaeological Association records
1980-1996
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 444
Montana Archaeological Association
0.8 linear feet of shelf space.
The MAA was founded in 1980, and its membership was limited to professional archaeologists only. The records (1980-1996) consist of: organizational records, financial records, membership records, general correspondence, as well as project and subject files.
Historical Note
Most members of the Montana Archaeological Association tended to belong to the Montana Archaeological Society as well, but the MAA being entirely made up of professional archaeologists, they were able to concentrate their efforts onto more specialized areas of interest. Some of the major causes undertaken by the MAA include the Native American Free Exercise of Religion Act, the Burial Bill Act and the Montana Antiquities Act among others. The MAA worked diligently to sponsor laws and to create guidelines for the ethical issues relating to archaeological work. The group worked closely with the Montana State Historic Preservation Office (SHPO), and in 1991 MAA and SHPO co-sponsored the first annual Archaeology Week in the state of Montana. This recurring event quickly became an important staple in the promotion of public awareness and education relating to local archaeology.
The Montana Archaeological Association found it increasingly difficult to continue its lobbying activities and sponsorship of the Archaeology Week program while relying strictly on volunteers. In 1996, the MAA, having never officially incorporated itself as an organization under Montana state law, elected to dissolve and to delegate all of its interests and activities to the MAS. Since the membership of both groups overlapped, the transition was smooth and the Montana Archaeological Society assumed all responsibility related to the sponsorship of Archaeology Week, as well as a more pronounced role in the political lobbying that had been such an important facet of the MAA. The two groups officially merged together after members approved the decision at their annual spring meetings in 1996.
The Montana Archaeological Association records (1980-1996) include: organizational records (1980-1996), such as by-laws and minutes; financial records (1980-1995) including bank statements; general correspondence (1980-1996), relating to the various programs sponsored by the group; membership records (1980-1989); and project and subject files relating to various tasks undertaken by the group in relation to lobbying and outreach.
Arranged by series. Some material housed in multimedia cabinet. See inventory below for more informaton.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
See also MC 349, Montana Archaeological Society records.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings. (Change the encoding analog as needed to accommodate the appropriate MARC code)
Montana Archaeological Association
Archaeology--Law and legislation--United States; Archaeology--Montana; Archaeology--Societies
Montana; Archaeology; Montana
- Organizational Records
  - By-Laws, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Minutes, 1980-1996 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - 1990 Minutes [audio] (Multimedia 68)
- Membership Records
  - Membership Lists, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Membership Lists, undated (Box-folder 1 / 5)
- Financial Records
  - Treasurer’s Reports, 1980-1995 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Bank Records, 1980-1987 (Box-folder 1 / 7-9)
- General Correspondence
  - General Correspondence, 1980-1994 (Box-folder 1 / 10-24)
  - MAA/MAS Merger, 1996 (Box-folder 1 / 25)
- Project Files
  - Programmatic Memorandum of Agreement on the Federal Coal Program, 1982 (Box-folder 1 / 26)
  - Montana Antiquities Act, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 27)
  - RP3 Report, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 1 / 28)
  - Trails to the Past: Financial Records, 1991 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Trails to the Past: General Correspondence, 1991 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - Trails to the Past: MCH Grant, 1991 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - Trails to the Past: Miscellany, 1991 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Burial Bill Act, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 2 / 5-6)
  - Burial Bill: Correspondence, 1988-1992 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Burial Bill: Clippings, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Montana Wilderness Bill, 1993 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - Native American Free Exercise of Religion Act, 1993 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
- Subject Files
  - Annual Meeting, 1980-1993 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Professional Service Directories, 1981-1994 (Box-folder 2 / 12-14)
  - Professional Service Directory: Correspondence, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
- Miscellany
  - Miscellany, 1984 (Box-folder 2 / 16)
  - Archaeomagnetic Services, 1985 (Box-folder 2 / 17)
  - Newsletter, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 2 / 18)
  - Miscellany, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 2 / 19)
  - Source of MS Report, undated (Box-folder 2 / 20)